<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word without-doors concerning the bill for succession</title>
            <author>J. D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D49A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204199</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899894</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899894</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135363</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82026)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135363)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2479:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word without-doors concerning the bill for succession</title>
                  <author>J. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: J.D.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Concerns the succession of the Duke of York to the throne.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135363:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A WORD Without-Doors Concerning the BILL FOR SUCCESSION.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am very ſenſible of the great honour you were pleaſed to do me in your laſt, which I received immediately after our late unhappy Diſſolution; but could have wiſhed you would have laid your Commands on ſome more able perſon, to have given you ſatisfaction in the matter you there propoſe rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Duke, who, you ſeem to inſinuate, was like (if the Parliament had continued) to have received hard meaſure. I muſt ingenuouſly confeſs to you, I was not long ſince perfectly of your opinion, and thought it the higheſt injuſtice imaginable, for any Prince to be debar'd of his native Right of Succeſſion upon any pretence whatſoever. But upon a more mature deliberation and enqiry, I found my errour proceeded principally from the falſe notions I had took up of Government it ſelf, and from my ignorance of the practices of all Communities of men in all ages, whenever ſelf-preſervation and the neceſſity of their affairs obliged them to declare their opinion in caſes of the like nature: To the the knowledge of all which, the following Accident I ſhall relate to you, did very much contribute.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:135363:2"/>
            <p>My occaſions obliging me one day to attend the coming of a Friend in a Coffee-houſe near <hi>Charing-croſs,</hi> there hapned to ſit at the ſame Table with me two ingenious Gentlemen, who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the frankneſs of Converſation now uſed in the Town, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan a Diſcourſe on the ſame ſubject you deſire to be more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly informed in; and having extolled the late Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons as the beſt number of men that had ever ſat within thoſe Walls; and that no Houſe had ever more vigorouſly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and aſſerted Engliſh Liberty and Proteſtant Religion than they had done, as far as the nature of the things that came before them, and the circumſtances of time would admit, (to all which I very readily and heartily aſſented:) They then added, That the great Wiſdom and Zeal of that Houſe had appeared in nothing more, than in ordering a Bill to be brought in for debarring the Duke of <hi>Y.</hi> from inheriting the Crown. A Law they affirmed to be the moſt juſt and reaſonable in the world, and the only proper Remedy to eſtabliſh this Nation on a true and ſolid Intereſt, both in relation to the preſent and future times.</p>
            <p>To which I could not but reply, That I begged their pardon, if I differed from them in opinion; and did believe, that how ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſoever the Houſe of Commons might intend in that matter, yet that the point of Succeſſion was ſo ſacred a thing, and of ſo high a nature, that it was not ſubjected to their cognizance: That Monarchy was of Divine Right: That Princes ſucceeded by nature and generation onely, and not by authority, admiſſion, or approbation of the People; and conſequently, that neither the merit or demerit of their perſons, nor the different influences from thence upon the People, were to be reſpected or had in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but the Common-wealth ought to obey and ſubmit to the next Heir, without any further inquiſition; and if he proved a worthy, vertuous, and juſt Prince, it was a great happineſs; if unjuſt, barbarous, and tyrannical, there was no other remedy, but prayer, patience, and an entire ſubmiſſion to ſo difficult a diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods Providence.</p>
            <p>I had no ſooner ended my diſcourſe, but one of the Gentlemen (that was the moſt ſerious in the company) ſeeing me a young man, gravely replyed, That he could not but be extremely concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to hear that ſuch pernicious Notions againſt all lawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment had been taught in the world: That he believed they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135363:2"/>were in me purely the effects of an Univerſity-Education; and that it had been my misfortune to have had a very high Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for my Tutor, who had endeavoured (as it was their conſtant practice to all young Gentlemen under their care) to debauch me with ſuch principles as would enſlave my mind to their Hierarchy and the Monarchical part of the Government, without any regard at all to the Ariſtocratical and Popular; and that fat Parſonages, Prebendſhips, Deanaries, and Epiſcopal Sees, were the certain and conſtant Rewards of ſuch Services: That the place we were in, was a little too publick for diſcourſes of this nature; but if I would accept of a Bottle of Wine at the next Tavern, he would undertake to give me juſter meaſures; adding, It was pity ſo hopeful a Gentleman ſhould be tainted with bad Principles. My Friend coming in at the ſame time, proved to be one of their particular Acquaintance; and both he and I readily complied with ſo generous a motion.</p>
            <p>We had no ſooner drank a Glaſs round, but the old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was pleaſed to renew his diſcourſe, and ſaid, It was undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly true, that the inclination of Mankind to live in company (from whence come Towns, Cities, and Common-wealths) did proceed of Nature, and conſequently of God, the Author of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. So likewiſe Government, and the Juriſdiction of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in general (which does neceſſarily flow from the living together in ſociety) is alſo of Nature, and ordained by God for the common good of Mankind; but that the particular ſpecies and forms of this or that Government, in this or that manner, to have many, few, or one Governour; or that they ſhould have this or that Authority, more or leſs, for a longer or a ſhorter time; or whether ordinarily by Succeſſion or by Election, all theſe things (he ſaid) are ordained and diverſified by the particular poſitive Laws of every Country, and are not eſtabliſht either by Law Natural or Divine, but left by God unto every Nation and Country, to pitch upon what form of Government they ſhall think moſt proper to promote the common Good of the whole, and beſt adapted to the natures, conſtitutions, and other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the People; which accordingly for the ſame reaſons may be altered or amended in any of its parts, by the mutual conſent of the Governours and governed, whenever they ſhall ſee reaſonable cauſe ſo to do: all which appears plainly, both from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135363:3"/>the diverſity of Governments extant in the world, and by the ſame Nations living ſometimes under one ſort of Government, and ſometimes under another. So we ſee God himſelf permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his peculiar People the <hi>Jews</hi> to live under divers forms of Government; as firſt under Patriarchs, then under Captains, then under Judges, then under High-Prieſts, next under Kings, and then under Captains and High-Prieſts again, until they were conquered by the <hi>Romans,</hi> who themſelves alſo firſt lived under Kings, and then Conſuls, whoſe authority they afterwards limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a Senate, by adding Tribunes of the people; and in extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary emergencies of the Common-wealth, they were gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Dictators, and laſt of all by Emperours. So that it's plain, no Magiſtrate has his particular Government, or an Intereſt of Succeſſion in it, by any Inſtitution of Nature, but onely by the particular Conſtitution of the Common-wealth within it ſelf. And as the kinds of Government are different, ſo alſo are the meaſures of Power and Authority in the ſame kind, in different Countries.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin (ſaid he) with that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, which though it be the firſt in dignity amongſt Chriſtian Princes, yet it is ſo reſtrained and limited by the particular Laws of the Empire, that he can do much leſs in his State, than other Kings in theirs. He can neither make War, nor exact any Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Men or Money, but by the conſent of all the States of the <hi>German</hi> Diet: And as for his Children and Relations, they have no intereſt or pretence to ſucceed, but onely by Election, if they ſhall be thought worthy. Nay, the chiefeſt Article the Emperour ſwears to keep at his admiſſion to that Honour, is, That he ſhall never endeavour to make the Dignity of the Empire Hereditary to his Family.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Spain</hi> and in <hi>France</hi> the Priviledges of Kings are much more eminent, both in Power and ſucceſſion; their Authority is more abſolute, every Order of theirs having the validity of a Law, and their next of bloud does ordinarily inherit, though in a different manner. In <hi>Spain</hi> the next Heir cannot ſucceed, but by the approbation of the Nobility, Biſhops, and States of the Realm. In <hi>France</hi> the Women are not admitted to ſucceed, let them be never ſo lineally deſcended. In <hi>England</hi> our Kings are much more limited and confined in their Power, than either of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135363:3"/>the two former: for here no Law can be made, but by conſent and authority of Parliament; and as to the point of Succeſſion, the next of kin is admitted, unleſs in extraordinary caſes, and when important Reaſons of State require an alteration: And then the Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> (according to the ancient Laws and Statutes of the Realm) have frequently directed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the ſucceſſion of the Crown in other manner than in courſe it would have gone; of which I ſhall give you ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in order.</p>
            <p>But firſt let us look abroad, and ſee how things have been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, as to this point, in other Countries.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Laws of Succeſſion did ordinarily hold; and accordingly <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> the lawful Son and Heir of <hi>Solomon,</hi> after his Fathers deceaſe, went to <hi>Sichem</hi> to be crowned and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the People: and the whole body of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> being there gathered together, did (before they would admit him their lawful King) make unto him certain Propoſitions for taking away ſome heavy Taxes that had been impoſed on them by his Father <hi>Solomon;</hi> which he refuſing to gratifie them in, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the advice of young men, ten of the Twelve Tribes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately choſe <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> a Servant of <hi>Rehoboam</hi>'s, a meer ſtanger, and of mean Parentage, and made him their King; and God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved thereof, as the Scriptures in expreſs words do teſtifie: for when <hi>Rehoboam</hi> had raiſed an Army of One hundred and four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore thouſand men, intending by force of Arms to have juſtified his Claim, God appeared unto <hi>Semajah,</hi> and commanded him to go to <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and to the Houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Return every man to his houſe, for this thing is of me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> So that ſince God did permit and allow this in his own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, which was to be the Pattern for all others, no doubt he will approve the ſame in other Kingdoms, whenever his ſervice and glory, or the happineſs of the Weal-publick ſhall require it.</p>
            <p>The next Inſtance I ſhall give you, ſhall be in <hi>Spain,</hi> where <hi>Don Alonſo de la Cerda</hi> having been admitted Prince of <hi>Spain</hi> in his Father's life-time (according to the cuſtom of that Realm) married <hi>Blancha,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Lewis</hi> the firſt King of <hi>France,</hi> and had by her two Sons named <hi>Alonſo</hi> and <hi>Hernando de la Cerda;</hi> but their Father (who was only Prince) dying before <hi>Alonſo</hi> the ninth then King, he recommended them to the Realm as lawful Heirs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135363:4"/>apparent to the Crown: But Don <hi>Sancho</hi> their Fathers younger Brother, who was a great Warrier, and ſirnamed <hi>El Bravo,</hi> was admitted Prince, and they put by, in their Grandfathers life-time, by his and the States conſent; and this was done at a Parliament held at <hi>Segovia,</hi> in the year 1276: And in the year 1284, (<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonſo</hi> the ninth being dead) Don <hi>Sancho</hi> was acknowledg'd King, and the two Princes impriſoned; but at the Mediation of <hi>Philip</hi> the third, King of <hi>France,</hi> their Uncle, they were ſet free, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with conſiderable Revenues in Land; and from them do deſcend the Dukes <hi>de Medina Celi</hi> at this day; and the preſent K. of <hi>Spain</hi> that is in poſſeſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> deſcendeth from Don <hi>Sancho.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>France, Lewis</hi> the fourth had two Sons, <hi>Lothairin,</hi> who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him, and <hi>Charles,</hi> whom he made Duke of <hi>Lorrain. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thairin</hi> dying, left an only Son named <hi>Lewis,</hi> who dying without Iſſue after he had raigned two years, the Crown was to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended on his Uncle <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorrain.</hi> But the States of <hi>France</hi> did exclude him, and choſe <hi>Hugo Capetus,</hi> Earl of <hi>Paris,</hi> for their King; and in an Oration made by their Embaſſador to <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> did give an account of their Reaſons for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it is related by <hi>Belforeſt,</hi> a French Hiſtorian, in theſe very words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every man knoweth</hi> (<hi>Lord</hi> Charles) <hi>that the Succeſſion of the Crown and Kingdom of</hi> France, <hi>according to the ordinary Rights and Laws of the ſame, belongeth unto you, and not unto</hi> Hugh Capet <hi>now our King: But yet the ſame Laws which do give unto you ſuch Right of Succeſſion, do judge you alſo unworthy of the ſame; for that you have not endeavoured hitherto to frame your life according to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of thoſe Laws, nor according to the uſe and cuſtom of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of</hi> France; <hi>but rather have allied your ſelf with the</hi> Germains, <hi>our old Enemies, and have accuſtomed your ſelf to their vile and baſe Manners. Wherefore ſince you have abandoned and forſaken the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Virtue, Amity, and Sweetneſs of your Country, your Country has alſo abandoned and forſaken you; for we have choſen</hi> Hugh Capet <hi>for our King, and have put you by, and this without any ſcruple in our Conſcrences at all; eſteeming it far better, and more juſt, to live under</hi> Hugh Capet, <hi>the Poſſeſſor of the Crown, with enjoying the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient uſe of our Laws, Cuſtoms, Priviledges, and Liberties, than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you the next Heir, by Bloud, in Oppreſſion, ſtrange Cuſtoms, and Cruelty. For as they who are to make a Voyage in a Ship on a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135363:4"/>Sea, do not ſo much reſpect whether the Pilot claims Title to the Ship or no, but rather whether he be skilful, valiant, and like to bring them in ſafety to their ways end; even ſo our principal care is to have a good Prince to lead and guide us happily in this way of Civil and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick life; which is the end for which Princes are appointed.</hi> And with this Meſſage ended his Succeſſion and Life, he dying not long after in Priſon.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall come home, and give you an Inſtance or two in <hi>England</hi> ſince the Conqueſt, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Rufus,</hi> ſecond Son of <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of <hi>Lanfrank</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who had a great opinion of his Virtue and Probity, was admitted King by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Realm, his elder Brother <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then in the War at <hi>Jeruſalem. William</hi> dying, his younger Brother <hi>Henry,</hi> by his ingenuity and fair carriage, and by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> who had greateſt intereſt in the Nobility; and <hi>Maurice</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> a leading-man amongſt the Clergy, obtained alſo the Crown. And <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> was a ſecond time excluded. And though this King <hi>Henry</hi> could pretend no other Title to the Crown than the Election and Admiſſion of the Realm, yet he defended it ſo well, and God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered him with ſuch ſucceſs, that when his elder Brother <hi>Robert</hi> came to claim the Kingdom by force of Arms, he beat him in a Pitcht Battle, took him Priſoner, and ſo he died miſerably in Bonds.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> had one only Daughter named <hi>Maud,</hi> or <hi>Matilda,</hi> who was married to the Emperor; and he dying without Iſſue, ſhe was afterwards married to <hi>Geofrey Plantagenet</hi> Earl of <hi>Anjou</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> by whom ſhe had a Son named <hi>Henry,</hi> whom his Grand-father declared Heir-apparent to the Crown in his life-time; yet after his death, <hi>Henry</hi> was excluded, and <hi>Stephen</hi> Earl of <hi>Bulloine,</hi> Son of <hi>Adela,</hi> Daughter of <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> was by the States thought more fit to govern than Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> who was then but a Child. And this was done by the perſwaſion of <hi>Henry</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and at the ſollicitation of the Abbot of <hi>Glaſtenbury</hi> and others, who thought they might do the ſame lawfully, and with a good conſcience, for the publick good of the Realm.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:135363:5"/>
            <p>But the event did not prove ſo well as they intended: for this occaſioned great Factions and Diviſions in the Kingdom; for the quieting of which, there was a Parliament held at <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingford,</hi> which paſſed a Law, That <hi>Stephen</hi> ſhould be King only during his Life, and that Prince <hi>Henry</hi> and his Off-ſpring ſhould ſucceed him; and by the ſame Law debarred <hi>William</hi> Son of King <hi>Stephen</hi> from inheriting the Crown, and only made him Earl of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus did the Parliament diſpoſe of the Crown in thoſe days, which was in the year 1153. which ſufficiently proves what I have aſſerted.</p>
            <p>The ſum of all I have ſaid, amounts to this: That Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in general is by the Law of Nature, and conſequently the Ordinance of God; but that the different forms of Government, whether to reſide in one, few, or many; or whether it ſhall be continued by Succeſſion or by Election, together with the different meaſures and limitations of Power and Authority in Governours of the ſame kind in ſeveral Countries: all theſe things, I ſay, are ordained by, and purely depend upon poſitive and humane Laws. From whence it will neceſſarily follow, That the ſame humane Authority (reſiding in King, Lords, and Commons, here in <hi>England</hi>) which gave being to thoſe Laws for the good of the Community, is ſuperintendent over them, and both may and ought to make any addition to, or alteration of them, when the publick Good and Welfare of the Nation ſhall require it; unleſs you will admit, That an humane Authority, eſtabliſhing any thing intentionally for the common good of the Society, which in tract of time, by reaſon of unforeſeen circumſtances and emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, proves deſtructive of it, has by that Act concluded it ſelf, and made that accidental evil, moral and unchangeable; which to affirm, is ſenſleſs and repugnant.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:135363:5"/>
            <p>AND now, Sir, I hope by this time (ſaid the old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) you begin to think that the Bill for diſabling the Duke was not ſo unjuſt and unreaſonable as was pretended; and that the courſe of Succeſſion (being founded upon the ſame bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom with other Civil Conſtitutions) might likewiſe as juſtly have been altered by the King, Lords, and Commons, as any other Law or Cuſtom whatever.</p>
            <p>And here I might conclude: But becauſe a late PENTIONA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY Pen has publickly arraign'd the Wiſdom, Loyalty, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the honourable Houſe of Commons, on the account of this Bill, I will <hi>ex abundanti</hi> add a word or two more to that particular.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he pluckt a Paper out of his Pocket, entituled, <hi>Great and weighty Conſiderations relating to the Duke, and Succeſſor of the Crown,</hi> &amp;c. Which as ſoon as he had read unto us, You ſee here (ſaid he) the true temper of thoſe men, of whom I firſt gave you caution: There never was an endeavour (though in a Legal and Parliamentary way) after any Reformation either in Church or State, but the Promoters of it were ſure to be branded by them with the odions imputations of <hi>Fanaticiſm</hi> and <hi>Faction:</hi> Nay, if the Country-Electors of Parliament-men will not pitch upon ſuch Rake-hells of the Nation as are uſually propoſed by them, but on the contrary make uſe of their Freedom and Conſciences in chuſing able, upright, and deſerving perſons; and if good men thus choſen do but (according to their Duty in the Houſe) enquire into publick Grievances, purſue in a legal courſe notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Offenders, and conſult and adviſe the ſecurity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Proteſtant Religion, the high Church-man imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſwells, and in paſſion tells you, That all this proceeds from the old Phanatick-Leven, not yet worn out amongſt the people: That we are going back again to Forty one; and acting over afreſh the ſins of our Forefathers.</p>
            <p>Thus ignorantly do they complement the Times and Perſons they endeavour to expoſe, by appropriating to them ſuch Virtues as were common to good men in all Ages. But enough of this.</p>
            <p>In the next place, pray obſerve how hypocritically the <hi>CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIDERER</hi> puts this Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:135363:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether Proteſtant Religion was not ſetled in this Nation by the ſame mighty hand of God that eſtabliſht</hi> Jeroboam <hi>in the Kingdom of</hi> Iſrael? [And then adds,] <hi>Whether we (like that wicked King) ſhould ſo far deſpair of Gods Providence in preſerving the work of his own hands, as never to think it ſafe, unleſs it be eſtabliſht on the Quick-ſands of our own wicked Inventions?</hi> [<hi>viz.</hi> the Bill againſt the Duke.]</p>
            <p>And throughout his whole Diſcourſe he frequently calls all Care of preſerving our Religion, a Miſtruſt of God's Providence; and on that ſcore calls out to the Nation, <hi>O ye of little faith,</hi> &amp;c. Now I will allow him, That the leaſt evil is not to be done, that the greateſt and moſt important Good may enſue: But that the Bill for Diſabling the Duke is highly juſtifiable both by the Laws of God, and Conſtitution of our Government, I think by my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Diſcourſe I have left no room to doubt; and the <hi>Conſiderer</hi> having ſcarce attempted to prove the contrary, it's prepoſterouſly done of him to give us his Uſe of Reproof, before he has clear'd his Doctrine.</p>
            <p>However, I owe him many thanks for putting me in mind how Proteſtant Religion was firſt eſtabliſht here in <hi>England:</hi> It was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by the mighty hand of God influencing the Publick Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of the Nation, ſo that all imaginable care was taken both by Prince and People, to reſcue themſelves from under the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Yoke; and accordingly moſt excellent Laws were made againſt the Uſurpation and Tyranny of that Man of Sin. Our Noble Anceſtors in thoſe days did not palliate a want of zeal for their Religion with a lazy pretence of truſting in Gods Providence; but together with their Prayers to, and Affiance in Heaven, they joined the acts of their own Duty, without which, (they very well know) they had no reaſon to expect a bleſſing from it.</p>
            <p>But now be pleaſed to take notice of the Candor of this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Conſiderer;</hi> Nothing leſs will ſerve his turn, than the proving all the Voters for the Bill guilty of the higheſt Perjury: <hi>For</hi> (ſays he) <hi>they have all ſworn in the Oath of Allegiance to bear Faith and true Allegiance to His Majeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors: But the Duke is Heir,</hi> Ergo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A very hopeful Argument indeed! But
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135363:6"/>what if it ſhould happen (as it is neither impoſſible, nor very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable to imagine it) that the next Heir to the Crown ſhould commit Treaſon, and conſpire the death of the preſent Poſſeſſor, and for this Treaſon ſhould not only be Attainted by Parliament, but Executed too; pray, Mr. <hi>Conſiderer,</hi> would the Parliament in this caſe be guilty of Murder and Perjury? I am confident you will not ſay it. If therefore the next Heir become obnoxious to the Government in a lower degree, why may not the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority proportion the puniſhment, and leave him his Life, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar him of the Succeſſion? This I ſay only to ſhew the abſurdity of his Argument.</p>
            <p>My Anſwer is this: No man can bear Allegiance to two perſons at the ſame time; nor can Allegiance be ever due to a Subject, and therefore my obligation by the word <hi>[Heir]</hi> in the Oath; does not commence till ſuch Heir has a preſent Right to, or actual poſſeſſion of the Crown; which if he never attains, either by reaſon of death, or any other Act that incapacitates and bars him, then can my obligation to him by the word <hi>Heir</hi> in the Oath never have a beginning.</p>
            <p>But beſides all this, it cannot be denyed but that Mr. <hi>Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi>'s Doctrine does bring great inconveniencies on Succeſſion; for the next Heir (by his way of arguing) is let looſe from all the Reſtrictions and Penalties of Humane Laws; and has no other tyes upon him not to ſnatch the Crown out of the hands of the Poſſeſſor, than purely thoſe of his own Conſcience; which is worthy Mr. <hi>Conſiderer</hi>'s higheſt conſideration.</p>
            <p>I ſhall onely take notice of one Objection more, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, (fearing I have too much treſpaſſed on your patience al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It's very hard</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that a man ſhould loſe his Inheritance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is of this or that perſwaſion in matters of Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly Gentlemen, were the caſe only ſo, I ſhould be entirely of his mind. But alas! Popery (whatever Mr. <hi>Conſiderer</hi> is pleas'd to inſinuate) is not an harmleſs innocent perſwaſion of a number of men differing from others in matters relating to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion; but is really and truly a different Religion from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135363:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſtianity it ſelf. Nor is the Inheritance he there mentions, an Inheritance onely of <hi>Black Acre</hi> and <hi>White Acre,</hi> without any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice annexed, which requires him to be <hi>par Officio:</hi> But the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Protection of ſeveral Nations, the making of War and Peace for them, the Preſervation of their Religion, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of publick Places and Revenues, the Execution of all Laws, together with many other things of the greateſt importance, are in this caſe claimed by the word <hi>Inheritance;</hi> which if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and at the ſame time reflect upon the enſlaving and bloody Tenets of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> more particularly the Helliſh and Damnable Conſpiracy thoſe of that Communion are now carrying on againſt our Lives, our Religion, and our Government; I am confident you will think it as proper for a Wolf to be a ſhepherd, as it is for a Papiſt to be the <hi>Defender of our Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The old Gentleman had no ſooner ended his Diſcourſe, but I returned him my hearty thanks, for the trouble he had been pleaſed to give himſelf on this occaſion; and I could not but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg he had given me great ſatisfaction in that affair; what it will give thee, <hi>Charles,</hi> I know not: I am ſure I parted from him very melancholy, for having been a Fool ſo long. <hi>Adieu.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am thy Affectionate,</hi> J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
